Finding Aid for George R. Pray Papers 1879-1941
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
George R. Pray Papers 1879-1941 1879-1899
Pray, George R. (George Raymond), 1878-1967.
3 linear ft.
Jackson, Michigan physician; medical practice records, correspondence, school materials, personal, and photographs
9424 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
This collection is part of a series of donations made by the Pray family (donor no. 4444 ).
The collection is open for research.
George Raymond Pray was born in Ionia June 16, 1878. His father was George W. Pray, one of the eleven members of the University of Michigan's first graduating class in 1845, and he followed in his father's footsteps by enrolling at Michigan in 1896. He was a member of the Phi Beta Pi medical fraternity, and in 1900 he received his medical degree. He worked as an intern at the University Hospital from 1900 to 1902, spending the latter two years as first assistant in gynecology and obstetrics. In 1902 he accepted a position as physician at the Michigan State Prison in Jackson. He married Zoe K. Porter around 1912. He kept a practice from his office at home for many years and retired from medicine in the summer of 1967. He died Christmas Eve, 1967.
The George R. Pray collection consists of five series: Medical Practice, Correspondence, School Materials, Personal, and Photographs.
Subjects:
Physicians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Physicians--Michigan--Jackson.; Pray, George R. (George Raymond), 1878-1967.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Medicine and Surgery.; University of Michigan--Students--Outlines, syllabi, etc.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Medical education.; Medicine--Michigan.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Medical Practice
  The Medical Practice series (2.0 linear feet) consists of published books, as well as record books created by Pray for his personal use and reference. The published books are primarily medical, used by Pray while in medical school at the close of the nineteenth century. These books, some including handwritten notes and annotations, give insight to medical practice and instruction of the period. Pray's record books, including his financial records, appointment books, and notebooks illustrate his organized nature and attention to detail. Also included in this series are miscellaneous newspapers from the Ann Arbor and the University of Michigan.
  - Financial Diaries, 1916-1939
    - 1916-1935, 20 volumes (Box 1)
    - Financial Diaries, 1936-1939, 4 volumes (Box 2)
  - Phonograph Record List (Box 2)
  - Pharmacology and Therapeutics by S.A. Matthews (Box 2)
  - Practical Notes on Urinary Analysis by W.B. Canfield (Box 2)
  - Outlines of Anatomy by William A. Campbell (Box 2)
  - Calendar of the University of Michigan for 1896-1897 (Box 2)
  - Palatable Prescribing by B.W. Palmer (Box 2)
  - Directions for Laboratory Work in Bacteriology by Frederick G. Novy (Box 2)
  - Lecture notebook-Bacteriology/General Anatomy (Box 2)
  - Chronic cases notebook, ca.1941 (Box 2)
  - A List of the Birds and Mammals Collected by the Steere Expedition to the Philippines by J.B. Steere (Box 2)
  - The Distribution of Genera and Species of Non-Migratory Land Birds in the Philippines by J.B. Steere (Box 2)
  - Michigan Medical Journal, 1902-1903 (Box 2)
  - Prescription book, 1901-1910 (Box 2)
  - Account books, 1911-1916, 2 books (Box 2)
  - Local newspapers and publications-miscellaneous, 1892-1899 (Box 2)
- Correspondence, 1879-1899
  The Correspondence series (0.6 linear feet) includes letters from friends and family received by Pray while in Ionia, Ann Arbor, and at Woodard Lake. Most concern school, health, and life back home. These letters span the years 1879-1899.
  - 1879-1899, 19 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence regarding diary of George W. Pray, 1924 (Box 3)
- School Material, 1880-1900
  The School Materials series (0.1 linear foot) spans the years 1880-1900 and consists of miscellaneous materials, including notes, grade reports, account transactions, and graduation announcements, primarily from the University of Michigan, but also from elementary school and Ann Arbor High School.
  - 1880-1900 (Box 3)
  - Medical School material, ca. 1899 (Box 3)
- Personal
  The Personal series (0.1 linear feet) includes miscellaneous items spanning Pray's life, including an obituary from the Foote Memorial Hospital bulletin, list of books read by 1894, dance and party invitations, and rosters from the Jackson Conopus Club.
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 3)
  - Invitations, 1895-1897 (Box 3)
  - Jackson Conopus Club, 1921-1922 (Box 3)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series (0.2 linear feet) consists primarily of portraits, but some snapshots and taxidermy photos are also included. Roughly half of the photo subjects are identified, but few appear to be members of the Pray family itself. The photographs are undated.
  - Portraits from Ionia, Owosso, and Ann Arbor (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous and Unidentified Photos, 5 folders (Box 3)
  - Taxidermy Photographs (Box 3)